A Finding Aid to the Ira Licht papers, 1963-1991, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Ira Licht papers
1963-1991
Archives of American Art
Licht, Ira Richard, 1938-
AAA.lichtira
Archival Resource Key
0.8 Linear feet
The Ira Licht papers measure 0.8 linear feet and date from 1963-1991. The papers document Licht's career as an art historian and museum professional. Included is professional and personal correspondence with artists during his career as curator at the Museum of Contemporary Art, Chicago, coordinator of Art in Public Places, National Endowment for the Arts, and tenure as director of the University of Miami's Lowe Art Museum. The letters are from many notable artists at early stages in their careers, which provides insight into how they built success from an early point. There are also artist and exhibition files which document working relationships with and about artists and exhibitions Licht curated, as well as printed materials such as exhibition invitations and posters.
Biographical / Historical
Ira Licht (1938- ) is a museum director, curator and art historian in Miami, Florida. During his career he served as the curator at the Museum of Contemporary Art, Chicago (1974-1976); coordinator of the Art in Public Places Program of the National Endowment for the Arts (1976-1978); and director of the University of Miami's Lowe Art Museum (1978-1989). Licht was closely connected with artists associated with 20th century minimalism, conceptualism, and land art. Artists who are represented by at least one piece of correspondence (postcards and/or letters) in the papers include: Duane Hanson, Pat Steir, Carl Andre, Ana Mendieta, Jackie Ferrara, Romare Bearden, Larry Bell, Robert Irwin, Adrian Piper, Lawrence Wiener, Dan Flavin, Laurie Anderson, Dan Graham, Robert Graham, Lynda Benglis, Dennis Oppenheim, Red Grooms and Christo.
Ira Licht is married to Jennifer Licht who was an associate curator at the Museum of Modern Art in New York.
Scope and Contents
The Ira Licht papers measure 0.8 linear feet and date from 1963-1991. The papers document Licht's career as an art historian and museum professional. Included is professional and personal correspondence with artists during his career as curator at the Museum of Contemporary Art, Chicago, coordinator of the Art in Public Places Program of the National Endowment for the Arts, and director of the University of Miami's Lowe Art Museum and relate to projects and funding. The letters are from many notable artists at early stages in their careers, which provides insight into how they built success from an early point. Some letters have photographs and printed material enclosed. Artist files are arranged alphabetically by name and include writings on and by artists, resumes and project descriptions, photographic prints, slides of artists' artwork, press clippings, correspondence and exhibition catalogs. Exhibition files consist of planning documents, exhibition catalogs, correspondence related to and press releases for exhibitions Licht curated. Of note is an catalog for Bodyworks a 1975 group exhibition Licht curated for the Museum of Contemporary Art, Chicago. The papers also include printed material which consists of exhibition announcements, invitations, and posters.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated in 2019 by Ira Licht.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 4 series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1969-1991 (0.3 Linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Artist and Exhibition Files, 1963-1991 (0.3 Linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1972-1984 (0.1 Linear feet; Box 2)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1967-1978 (0.1 Linear feet; Box 2)
Art museum directors -- Florida -- Miami; Art historians -- Florida -- Miami; Art museum curators; Lowe Art Museum; National Endowment for the Arts; Museum of Contemporary Art (Chicago, Ill.)
- Correspondence, 1969-1991; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains professional and personal correspondence with artists during Licht's career as curator at the Museum of Contemporary Art, Chicago, the coordinator of the Art in Public Places Program of the National Endowment for the Arts, and director of the University of Miami's Lowe Art Museum and relate to projects and funding.The letters are from many notable artists at early stages in their careers, which provides insight into how they built success from an early point. Some letters have photographs and printed material enclosed. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically.
  - Laurie Anderson, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Elanor Antin, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A, 1977; 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Larry Bell, 1975-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Andrea Blum, 1977-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Peter Blume, 1975-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Robert Breer, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - B, circa 1969-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - John Cage, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Canole, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Christo, 1976-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Jackie Ferrara, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Red Grooms, 1981; 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Duane Hanson, 1979-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - H, 1975-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Robert Indiana, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Philip Johnson, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Dennis Kowalski, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - L, 1975-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - M, 1977-1982; 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - N, 1977-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - P, 1975; 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - R, circa 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - S, 1970-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Michael Venezia, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - W, 1972; 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous, Last Name Unsigned, 1971-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Artist Files, 1963-1991; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Artist files are arranged alphabetically by name and include writings on and by artists, resumes and project descriptions, photographic prints, slides of artists' artwork, press clippings, correspondence and exhibition catalogs.
  - Vito Acconci, 1969-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Jennifer Bartlett, circa 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Lynda Benglis, 1921-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Scott Burton, circa 1970-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Lowell Darling, circa 1975-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Dan Flavin, circa 1963-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
  - Dan Graham, circa 1972-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Robert Graham, circa 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Hans Haacke, 1972; 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Hans Hofmann, circa 1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Loren Madsen, circa 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mary Miss, 1976-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Claes Oldenburg, circa 1963-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dennis Oppenheim, 1969-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Alan Saret, circa 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Italo Scanga, 1970; 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Paul Sharits, 1972-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Exhibition Files, 1972-1984; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Exhibition files are arranged alphabetically by name and consist of planning documents, exhibition catalogs, correspondence related to and press releases for exhibitions Licht curated. Of note is an exhibition catalog for Bodyworks a 1975 group exhibition Licht curated for the Museum of Contemporary Art, Chicago.
  - Art Without Limit (1972), Memorial Art Gallery, University of Rochester, Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Bodyworks (Mar. 8 - Apr. 27, 1975), Museum of Contemporary Art Chicago, Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - George Segal Sculpture (Mar.9- Apr. 24, 1983), Lowe Art Museum, University of Miami, 1981-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Robert Irwin (Nov. 8, 1975 - Jan. 4, 1976), Museum of Contemporary Art, Chicago, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Printed Material, 1967-1978; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 2
  Printed material consists of exhibition announcements, invitation cards and posters.
  - Exhibition Announcements and Invitation Cards, circa 1975-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Exhibition Posters, circa 1967-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)